Imagine looking at the Roman Empire, like the very day before it fell, and then you look at Silicon Valley today, and you realize that mathematically, and I mean down to the exact geometric equation, they are making the exact same fatal mistake.
It's a pretty wild thought.
It's mind-bending, because normally we treat these things as completely different chapters of history, right? I mean, you have the rise of humanity, the violent collapse of an empire, and now the looming shadow of artificial superintelligence.
Yeah, completely different fields of study.
Exactly. We have biology for our origins, history for our empires, and computer science for our future.
Well, it's comforting to categorize the world like that. You know, we like our domains siloed, each with its own specific experts and its own safe, isolated narrative.
Right.
But the problem with complex systems is that they just don't respect our academic boundaries.
No, they really don't. And when you step into the world of complex systems and mathematical geometry, those silos just completely dissolve.
They absolutely do.
Which brings us to our mission for today, because we're looking at a predictor landscape today that is honestly, well, it's staggering.
What if you could predict the rise of human cooperation, the internal rot of a superpower, and the ultimate existential threat of a rogue AI, all using the exact same underlying mathematical architecture?
It fundamentally changes how you perceive risk.
I mean, we're talking about a paradigm shift in how we analyze reality itself.
The underlying structure governing all these seemingly disconnected events is actually identical.
Okay, let's unpack this, because we are jumping into a highly dense, absolutely fascinating deep dive today.
We're looking at an independent research paper by an author named Fliction.
It's titled Civilizations as Reachability Systems.
And it's incredibly ambitious.
It is. It takes three major, completely distinct books.
So that's Peter Turchin's Ultra Society, his follow-up Ages of Discord, and Darren McKee's Uncontrollable.
And it unites them into one master mathematical theory.
Right. And just to give that some context for everyone, Turchin's Ultra Society is conventionally read as this deep dive into how large-scale human cooperation evolved over the last 10,000 years.
Right. Pre-history into history.
Exactly. And then his next book, Ages of Discord, analyzes why complex societies collapse internally.
So the cyclical destabilization that brings down empires.
The fall of Rome kind of stuff.
Yeah, exactly.
And then McKee's Uncontrollable is a contemporary text that's entirely focused on the alignment problem of artificial superintelligence.
So we're spanning prehistory, recorded history, and the immediate future.
All in one paper.
Right.
So to you, listening right now, putting human evolution, the fall of Rome, and rogue AI into the same mathematical equation might sound, I don't know, like pure science fiction.
This does sound like sci-fi.
But we are going to look at history today, not through dates or battles or great leaders.
We are looking through something the paper calls admissible future manifolds.
Which is a heavy term.
It is.
But the central question we have to wrestle with today is actually quite simple, even if the math is complex.
Right.
And that question is, what expands, contracts, or irreversibly closes the space of futures available to a civilization?
I love how you phrase that.
Well, by the end of this deep dive, the goal is to equip you with a completely new framework for analyzing the world around you.
Whether that's global geopolitics or, honestly, just the trajectory of your own career.
Yeah.
We are mapping the invisible architecture of what is actually possible.
The invisible architecture of the possible.
That is, that's a great way to put it.
But to start building this framework, we have to lay down some foundational geometry.
I promise we wouldn't drown anyone in jargon, but we absolutely need to define a couple of core concepts to get off the ground.
We do.
Starting with something the paper calls state space.
Right.
So think of state space not as physical space.
We aren't talking about galaxies or solar systems here.
No spaceships.
Think of it as an abstract mathematical arena.
In this arena, every single point represents a possible configuration of a civilization.
Okay, give me a tangible example of that.
How do I visualize a configuration?
Let's use a chess board first.
The state space of a chess game is every legally possible arrangement of pieces on that board.
Oh, okay.
So millions of possibilities.
Exactly.
Millions of points in that state space.
Now, scale that up to a society.
Right.
If your society has, say, a certain population size, a specific legal code,
a certain level of agricultural technology, and a specific wealth distribution.
All of those variables combine to place you at one single specific point in the state space.
Okay, I follow that.
So if a massive famine hits, and half the population leaves,
our society moves to a completely different point in the state space.
Right.
Or if we invent the steam engine, we jump to another point.
Correct.
State space is the entire theoretically possible universe of conditions a society could ever find itself in.
The whole map.
But, and this is a crucial caveat, you cannot just teleport anywhere on that map.
What do you mean?
Well, if you are a Bronze Age tribe, you cannot suddenly jump to the space-faring civilization point in the state space.
You have to navigate there step by step from where you currently are.
Oh, right.
You're constrained by reality.
Exactly.
Which brings us to the second concept, and I spent a lot of time shooing on this one
because it's arguably the most important idea in the whole paper, the forward admissible cone.
Yes.
It's a concept borrowed from viability theory, and it is brilliant in its application here.
Unpack it for us.
So, for any state your civilization is currently occupying, the forward admissible cone is a geometric shape.
Literally a cone radiating outward from your current position into the future.
Radiating forward.
Right.
And it represents the immediate safe directions your society can move without hitting a wall.
And when we say wall, we aren't talking about a physical brick wall, obviously.
No, no.
We mean an existential constraint, like an institutional collapse, a hard ecological boundary, a total economic failure.
The cone is the set of trajectories you can take that are actually practically viable without causing a collapse.
Let me try an analogy here because I really want you, the listener, to visualize this.
Go for it.
Picture yourself driving a car down a very steep winding mountain path.
Okay.
There's a sheer cliff on your left side and a solid rock wall on your right.
The cone we are talking about is the range of angles you can safely turn your steering wheel that will keep you on the paved road.
That's a great visual.
Right.
Because if you steer within that narrow cone, you keep driving forward into the future.
But if you steer outside the cone-like, if you yank the whale too hard to the left or right, you either hit the rock wall or you fly off the cliff.
You violated a constraint.
Exactly.
You are no longer on an admissible trajectory.
You're dead.
It is a highly accurate visualization.
The paper explicitly defines an admissible trajectory as a path where your movement always stays inside that safe cone over time.
And if you map out the total collection of all the safe places you could eventually reach by staying within the cone, step after step, generation after generation.
What's that called?
That totality is called the admissible future manifold.
It is the entire landscape of your reachable future.
The entire landscape.
But mountain roads aren't always wide, easy highways.
No, they are not.
Sometimes the road narrows.
Sometimes a landslide blocks half the lane.
And that is where the geometry gets incredibly revealing.
Because the paper introduces the mathematics of what happens when that road narrows.
It details Proposition 2, boundary curvature in bottleneck geometry.
Bottleneck geometry.
I read this part like three times because the math felt so ominous to me.
How does it actually work?
Let's stick with your mountain road.
Okay.
When the road is wide, your forward admissible cone is wide.
You have a massive range of safe steering angles.
Right.
I can drift a little to the left to look at the view, drift to the right to avoid a pothole.
Exactly.
You have plenty of room for air.
The steering effort required to just survive is minimal.
But what happens when the path narrows into a tiny single lane bottleneck with a sheer drop on both sides?
The walls close in.
The cone shrinks.
The range of safe steering angles gets terrifyingly tiny.
Okay.
So mathematically, what's happening there?
Mathematically, as the angle of that safe cone approaches zero, the curvature of the boundary diverges toward infinity.
Infinity.
In your analogy, curvature is the per se steering effort required to avoid a fatal crash.
Oh, wow.
When your options narrow, the sheer navigational effort required just to stay alive becomes infinitely high.
Small, everyday mistakes suddenly become instantly fatal.
Wait, hold on.
I'm struggling to see how this translates from like a mathematical steering wheel to actual human leadership.
How so?
Well, are we saying that every historical crisis just requires a genius leader with infinite steering precision to get through it?
Because that sounds more like the great man theory of history than math.
Oh, that's a great distinction to make.
No, the math is actually arguing the exact opposite.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
It's saying that when the structural curvature diverges toward infinity, no leader is good enough to guarantee survival.
Oh.
The system itself becomes hyper-fragile.
It doesn't matter if you have a genius at the wheel.
If the safe steering angle is a fraction of a millimeter, eventually human error will send the car off the cliff.
So it's about the structure of the situation, not the skill of the driver.
Exactly.
Let's bring in a real-world strategic equivalent to make this concrete.
Please.
The paper links this mathematical curvature to a concept from the legendary Intel CEO, Andy Grove.
Oh, the inflection point.
Yes.
He talked extensively about strategic inflection points.
In Grove's framework, an inflection point is a moment where a business or a civilization faces a massive structural shift in its environment.
Like when the internet was invented and suddenly every print media company realized their mountain road just disappeared.
Exactly.
Or a sudden permanent resource shortage.
In the language of Fliction's paper, a strategic inflection point is a moment of extreme reachability curvature.
The safe cone has shrunk drastically due to external forces.
The road got narrow.
The road got extremely narrow.
At that precise moment in time, tiny positional changes, a slight tweak in corporate strategy, a minor government policy decision, produce massive irreversible shifts in what futures remain accessible.
Because you're right on the edge of the cliff.
Right.
If you don't steer with near infinite precision during that specific bottleneck, your admissible future manifold drops to zero, you go bankrupt.
You collapse.
Think about Intel in the 1980s.
I mean, Japanese companies started dominating the memory chip market.
Right.
And Intel was a memory company.
That was their whole road.
Suddenly, the road narrowed to zero.
Grove and Gordon Moore had to make an agonizing, incredibly precise turn to abandon memory entirely and switch to microprocessors.
Which was a massive risk.
Huge.
If they steered even slightly wrong or hesitated for six months, Intel would not exist today.
That is infinite curvature.
It is.
And very few entities survive moments of infinite curvature through sheer luck or perfect steering.
So how do you survive the tightrope walk, then?
You build safety nets into the geometry before you get to the tightrope.
Ah.
And that brings us to the final piece of our foundational framework.
Repair corridors.
The safety nets.
The emergency backups.
Exactly.
The paper defines a repair corridor as a specific, viable pathway that allows a system to navigate from a state of acute danger back into a safe region of the state space.
Okay.
It's a route to recovery, where forward motion remains mathematically possible the whole time.
You aren't just freezing in place.
You are actively moving towards safety.
Right.
And crucially, the paper emphasizes the need for robust repair corridors.
What makes it robust, as opposed to just a regular repair corridor?
A robust corridor is one that doesn't disappear just because of a slight miscalculation.
If you get bumped slightly off course by an unpredictable shock, a robust repair corridor is wide enough that it's still there to catch you.
Okay.
Bringing it back to the car on the mountain.
A repair corridor is like an emergency runaway truck ramp.
Perfect.
Yes.
Right.
Like if you're barreling down a steep grade and your brakes suddenly fail, which is a massive shock to your system, you have a predefined safe path you can steer into.
The runaway ramp.
Exactly.
The ramp absorbs the shock, slows you down using gravel, and prevents you from flying off the cliff.
And a robust repair corridor means the ramp is wide enough and clearly marked enough that even if your car is violently fishtailing, you can still manage to hit it.
That visual captures the math perfectly, and this concept is vital for everything, from global supply chains to ecological conservation.
Yeah.
The health of a civilization isn't just about how fast it's driving down the road.
It's about how many robust repair corridors it has proactively built into its landscape.
Right, because if you don't have them...
A society with no runaway ramps has to drive perfectly forever, and no one drives perfectly forever.
No one.
Which is an incredible segue into the next massive idea here, because if building these robust repair corridors is the key to survival, how do we actually know if a society has enough of them?
How do you measure the invisible?
Exactly.
How do you measure it?
The paper argues there are two vital metrics we must track, two master variables that dictate the destiny of any complex system.
All right.
The first is volume, and the second is entropy.
Specifically, weighted reachability volume, which the paper denotes algebraically as VR, and reachability entropy, denoted as HR.
Okay, let's unpack volume first.
Weighted reachability volume.
In layman's terms, this is just the sheer size of your accessible future, correct?
Essentially, yes.
It is the raw scale of possibility.
Volume measures how much future you have.
If you look at the state space map, how many different safe conditions can your society realistically reach from where it is standing today?
That makes sense.
But we have to pay attention to the weighted part of the term.
The paper applies a robustness weight to these potential futures.
Meaning not all futures are created equal.
Far from it.
If a specific future requires extreme painful repair costs to reach, say, you can survive a famine, but only by eating all your seed grain and sacrificing a generation.
No.
Or if the safe cone leading to that future is paper thin and requires infinite curvature to navigate, the math assigns it a much lower weight.
Because it's barely a viable option.
Exactly.
So VR isn't just a naive, raw count of every theoretical possibility.
It's a realistic measure of the rich, accessible, realistically survivable futures you have at your disposal.
Okay.
So high volume is good.
We want a big, wide open future with lots of heavily weighted, easy to reach safe states.
Yeah.
But here is where the paper absolutely blew my mind and why I think everyone listening needs to pay really close attention to this next point.
Volume alone is not enough.
No.
In fact, optimizing only for volume might kill you.
You also need entropy.
And the author makes a brilliant intellectual leap here.
They import Shannon entropy, which is a concept originally from information theory and thermodynamics.
Right.
And they apply it to civilizational futures.
Reachability entropy doesn't measure how many futures there are.
It measures how qualitatively distinct those futures are from one another.
This is the absolute crux of the issue.
Let me translate this directly to you, the listener, maybe thinking about your career or your investments.
Okay.
Having high volume is like having a hundred different job offers sitting on your desk.
Sounds great.
Right.
You feel incredibly secure.
You have a hundred paths forward.
Your VR is massive.
Right.
But what if all 100 of those job offers are for the exact same position in the exact same fragile industry?
Say it's 1999 and you have a hundred lucrative offers to be a fax machine salesman.
Well, your volume is historically high, but your entropy is strictly zero.
Yes.
Because if that one specific industry crashes like, if email suddenly becomes ubiquitous, all 100 of your options vanish simultaneously.
Instantly.
The sheer number of offers didn't protect you at all because they weren't distinct.
High entropy, on the other hand, means having options in completely different, unconnected fields.
Right.
You have an offer in tech, an offer in agriculture, an offer in teaching.
They are qualitatively distinct pathways.
Exactly.
What's fascinating here is how the paper formalizes this in definition six.
It states that entropy is calculated over a macroscopic partition of qualitatively distinct future types.
Break that down for a nation state.
Sure.
Let's apply this to a nation state.
Different institutional regimes, different technological pathways, different energy sources.
If your society's entire economic future is concentrated into a single type, say, exporting a single natural resource like oil, your entropy is incredibly low.
Yeah.
Even if your bank accounts are currently full.
Even if your volume is huge.
Right.
But if your futures are spread across advanced manufacturing, software, agriculture, and renewable energy, your entropy is high.
Let me play devil's advocate here.
Sure.
Why do we humans always seem to sacrifice entropy for volume?
Because it feels like every corporation, every government naturally gravitates toward becoming the fax machine salesman.
That's a great question.
Because volume is easily measurable.
And it usually correlates with short-term efficiency and wealth.
If you dedicate all your farmland to a single, hyper-yielding crop, your volume goes through the roof.
Your quarterly earnings look amazing.
You look like a genius on paper.
Exactly.
Entropy, on the other hand, requires deliberate inefficiency.
Deliberate inefficiency.
Right.
It means planting crops that might not yield as much cash today just to ensure genetic diversity.
Entropy is an invisible safety net.
You only realize its value the moment you need it.
The classic example is the Irish potato famine in the 1840s.
A tragic but perfect example.
They maximized volume by planting the lumper potato because it grew incredibly well in poor soil and fed millions.
Right.
The volume was off the charts, but the entropy was practically zero because it was a monoculture.
Every single potato was essentially a genetic clone of the others.
Directly zero entropy.
So when the Phytothora and Festin's blight arrived, it didn't just kill some potatoes, it killed all of them.
The entire admissible future manifold collapsed overnight.
Because there were no distinct repair corridors.
There was no alternative crop infrastructure.
That historical tragedy perfectly maps onto the math.
A repair corridor is entirely useless if it relies on the exact same mechanism that just failed.
Obviously.
If your potato fails, your backup plan can't be plant more of the same potato.
Exactly.
You don't have a backup plan.
But if you have high entropy, if you have distinct pathways involving maritime trade or alternative grain agriculture or a robust industrial sector you can pivot to, you have independent repair corridors.
You can navigate around the constraint.
You survive.
So to summarize, volume is the sheer size of your safety net, but entropy is the diversity of the materials that nut is made of.
I like that.
If the net is huge, stretching for miles, but it's made entirely of a material that dissolves in water, the moment it starts raining, you're dead.
It's a visceral way to put it, but it's mathematically sound.
And the author leaves us with a profound thought on this in the paper's remark one.
They state that the deepest, most fundamental truth of a civilization isn't a number on a shred sheet.
It is the actual topology, the multidimensional geometric shape of its future space.
The shape of the future.
Right.
Volume and entropy are just our best human attempts to measure that shape.
They are scalar approximations, shadows on the cave wall of a massive hidden reality.
Okay.
We have our structural framework.
We understand state space, cones, repair corridors, volume, and entropy.
We have the tools.
Now, the paper takes this mathematical lens and does something wild.
It applies it to the entirety of human history.
It does.
So let's travel back to the dawn of civilization, unpacking the first of our three core books, Peter Turchin's Ultra Society.
Ultra Society is a monumental work.
It looks at the evolution of large-scale cooperation over the last 10,000 years.
Right.
How did humanity transition from roaming in small bands of a few dozen hunter-gatherers to building massive, globally interconnected civilizations of billions?
It's a huge leap.
It is.
And the conventional sociological and biological reading relies heavily on cultural group selection.
Which means what, exactly?
The idea is that groups of humans that develop strong cultural mechanisms to suppress selfish defection meaning,
they learn to cooperate and punish cheaters out-competed groups that couldn't cooperate.
Right.
The classic united we stand, divided we fall.
The cooperative tribe survives the winter.
The selfish tribe starves.
Exactly.
But Fliction's paper flips that conventional perspective on its head.
Okay.
How so?
It reframes the biological imperative as a geometric one.
The paper argues that what intergroup competition was actually selecting for wasn't just cooperation as some abstract moral good.
Evolution was physically selecting for societies that possessed larger reachability volume and higher reachability entropy.
Wow.
The math drove the evolution.
Yes.
Cooperation is merely the proximate social mechanism.
Expanded geometric future volume is the ultimate selected quantity.
There's a memorable quote from the source text that just hit me like a ton of bricks when I read it.
Which one?
The paper says,
A band cannot build a telescope.
A civilization can.
It's a beautiful distillation of the entire concept.
Let's unpack why that is.
Why can't a band build a telescope?
Think deeply about the state space required to reach the build a telescope point.
Yeah.
You need advanced mining techniques to get the ore.
You need metallurgy to forge the brass.
You need a deep understanding of optics and glassblowing.
You need advanced calculus and geometry.
You need a lot of distinct pathways.
And you need a massive, stable surplus of food to feed the scientists and artisans who are spending all day grinding lenses instead of hunting.
You need a stable legal system to protect the property and the knowledge over generations.
Right.
Because otherwise someone just steals the brass to make a spear.
Exactly.
A small band of 50 people, no matter how intelligent or morally cooperative they are,
simply does not possess a wide enough forward admissible cone to ever reach the telescope state.
The physics of their reality won't allow it.
They literally don't have the volume.
But when that tribe figures out how to scale up into a civilization of millions,
they unlock the division of labor.
One person farms, a thousand people mine, ten people grind lenses, and one person writes the math.
And by doing so, as the paper states, they physically expand the collective admissible manifold.
It's amazing.
The paper also explicitly mentions the evolutionary role of reverse dominance hierarchies.
I saw that.
What are those?
These are cultural systems where the group actively prevents a single tyrant or an alpha male from monopolizing all the resources and decision-making power.
Wait, so democracy, or at least the distribution of power, isn't just a moral triumph of the Enlightenment.
It's a mathematical hack for survival.
That is exactly what the geometry implies.
By distributing access to the future across the group, rather than concentrating all the reachability volume into the narrow whims of a single dictator,
the society as a whole unlocks vastly more distinct pathways.
Which means more entropy.
Exactly.
A dictator might only fund the military.
A distributed society funds the military, the arts, agriculture, and science.
They drastically increase their entropy.
But okay, this introduces a massive paradox.
What is it?
How does a society explore all these new, crazy technological and social pathways without accidentally destroying the very cooperation that got them there in the first place?
Right.
I mean, if you let people experiment with new ideas, some of those ideas might be, let's overthrow the government.
How do you invent the printing press, which fundamentally disrupts power, or the steam engine without shattering your social order and falling off the cliff?
This is where the paper weaves in biology again, specifically referencing the neutral network theorem.
I found this fascinating.
Explain how biological neutral networks map onto human societies.
The concept originates with evolutionary biologist Andreas Wagner.
In genetics, a neutral network is a vast, interconnected web of genetic mutations that an organism can undergo without altering its core, vital functions.
Okay, so it can change, but it doesn't die.
Right.
It can change its internal code.
It can drift around genetically, trying out millions of microscopic variations.
But the organism still survives and functions just fine in its current environment.
It isn't punished by natural selection for exploring these neutral states.
It's exploring the state space safely.
Exactly.
It's kind of like a jazz musician improvising over a bass line.
As long as they stay in key, the song doesn't collapse, even if they hit some weird notes.
That's a great way to think about it.
The paper's Proposition 4 applies this biological reality to human civilizations.
Okay.
A civilization with a large, robust, neutral network of safe, cooperative states has a massive frontier.
It has a massive playground.
It can experiment wildly.
Try new things.
It can try a new monetary policy.
It can invent a new philosophical movement.
It can restructure its local markets.
Because of the core cooperative function, the bass line, is deeply preserved.
The society can probe into the unknown without stepping outside its safe, admissible cone.
So let's look at the inverse of that.
Okay.
A hyper-rigid, traditional society that violently punishes any deviation from the norm-like,
a society that arrests anyone who suggests a new way of farming or a new way of governing,
has an infinitesimally small, neutral network.
Very small.
It can't explore.
It stagnates.
But a society that tolerates harmless deviance, that actively allows for safe experimentation,
builds this massive frontier.
Yes.
And from that wide frontier, they're statistically far more likely to stumble upon a brand new,
incredible future like the telescope or the internet.
The internet is a prime example.
The early protocols were developed by researchers funded by DARPA.
It was pure, undirected exploration.
Yeah, they were just messing around.
Exactly.
There was no immediate corporate mandate to maximize quarterly profits via a global network.
It was an exploration of the neutral network.
Right.
And according to the paper's theorem for repair generation, every time you discover a new,
viable pathway from that frontier, you generate a completely new repair corridor.
Ooh.
You literally add volume and entropy to your civilization's future.
You build a new runaway ramp.
Precisely.
Okay.
So that's the rise.
That's the expansion phase of humanity.
Yeah.
Mathematical geometry forces us to cooperate, scale up, and explore.
But if we just look at a history book, it isn't just a straight line going up forever.
Empires fall.
Rome burns.
The Han Dynasty collapses.
Everything cycles.
And that brings us to the second book the paper analyzes, Peter Turchin's Ages of Discord,
which is all about internal collapse.
Right.
So Turchin uses a framework called Structural Demographic Theory, or SDT, to track why seemingly
stable, powerful empires suddenly tear themselves apart.
And he tracks specific indicators, right?
He tracks long-term cyclical indicators, things like popular immiseration, which is the declining
living standards of the average citizen, and elite overproduction.
Elite overproduction is such a visceral term.
Let's make sure that's clear.
Yeah.
That's essentially when a society produces too many highly educated, ambitious, wealthy
people who are all competing for a rigidly fixed number of top leadership positions.
Imagine a society that produces 1,000 highly credentialed lawyers every year, but there
were only 10 open judge positions.
Okay.
You have 990 elites who feel they are owed a position of power, but the structure cannot
accommodate them.
It creates a high-stakes game of musical chairs.
Exactly.
But the 990 elites who don't get a chair don't just go home quietly, do they?
No, they don't.
They start actively trying to burn down the building, or they launch revolutions just to
create new chairs for themselves.
History is replete with revolutions led not by the starving peasants, but by the frustrated
second-tier elites.
But once again, Flixion's paper doesn't just settle for the historical narrative.
It translates this political dynamic into hard geometry.
Yes.
And here is where we get the most crucial, eye-opening deep dive of the entire document.
Example 1, the worked mathematical example of the CLIO projection.
Here's where it gets really interesting.
I want to walk through this math step-by-step with you, because when I understood this,
it felt like discovering the Rosetta Stone for why complex organizations fail.
It's profound.
Let's imagine two hypothetical societies.
Society 1 and Society 3.
Okay.
We're going to look at them first through the standard lens of structural demographic
theory, and then through the paper's geometric lens.
Let's say a standard historian is counting the total number of elites in both societies to
measure their structural mass.
For both Society 1 and Society 3, the total elite index is exactly 15.
15 elites each.
Yes.
To the standard historian or a modern economist looking at top-line volume metrics, these two
societies look completely identical.
Oh.
They appear to have the exact same capacity and the exact same level of stability.
They both have 15 power players.
So the normal metric says nothing to see here.
Everything is equal.
Exactly.
But then the paper forces us to look at the internal mathematical geometry.
We have to look at the entropy.
Right.
Let's break down Society 1.
Society 1 has a highly differentiated elite structure.
Let's say out of those 15 elites, 10 are in the scientific and institutional sector.
Meaning they run the universities, the infrastructure, that kind of thing?
Yes.
And the other five are in the military and administrative sector.
Okay.
So they have two distinct pools of expertise.
They have distinct types of futures they can access.
Precisely.
If we run the math and calculate the reachability entropy for Society 1 using Shannon's logarithmic
formula based on those distinct proportions, it comes out to roughly 0.918 bits.
0.918 bits of entropy.
Got it.
Now what about Society 3?
In Society 3, over time, the culture has homogenized.
Let's say an obsessive culture of single-minded political prestige has taken over.
Okay.
All 15 elites are pure prestige political elites.
Zero scientists.
Zero military tacticians.
Just 15 people fighting for the exact same political crown in the exact same arena.
Wow.
And the entropy for Society 3?
Strictly zero bits.
Zero.
Because there is no diversity of future types.
Exactly.
But let me play devil's advocate here.
Okay, go ahead.
I'm looking at Society 2 and I'm thinking, wait, in a crisis, wouldn't a highly unified
homogenous group of leaders actually be more efficient?
It seems that way, right?
Yeah.
I mean, they all speak the same language.
They all share the same values.
They wouldn't be constantly bickering across departments.
They'd act as one unified fist.
Why does the math say this unity is actually a death sentence?
It's a very common trap.
Unity of action is indeed efficient, but unity of capability is fatal.
Unity of capability.
Yes.
This is the core of the paper's theorem three, distinction collapse.
Let's say both Society 1 and Society 3 face a sudden massive shock.
Say, a novel agricultural virus that devastates the crop yield.
A crisis that requires a specific type of steering.
Exactly.
Society 1, with its 0.918 bits of entropy and its differentiated structure, has two structurally
distinct repair corridors.
It has options.
It can try to innovate its way out of the crisis using its 10 scientific elites.
Maybe they invent a new chemical fertilizer or genetically modify the crop.
That's one pathway.
Right.
Or if that fails, it can use its five military administrative elites to reallocate resources,
ration food, and secure borders to prevent mass rioting.
Two independent pathways to survival.
That makes total sense.
And what happens to Society 3 when the virus hits?
Society 3 has homogenized.
It only has one pathway.
Whatever the unified, prestige-obsessed political hierarchy can mobilize.
Which is just politics.
There is no independent fallback.
Fifteen politicians cannot pass a law that cures a plant virus.
Right.
If their single political pathway, perhaps just blaming a scapegoat or trying to buy food with
depleted treasury funds, fails to solve the crisis, the society collapses.
Because they have no other options.
Theorem 3 proves mathematically that when a society merges its distinct pathways into
a single homogenous system, usually in the name of efficiency or prestige, it destroys
its own entropy.
The illusion of stability.
This is the fax machine salesman with 100 job offers, but scaled up to an entire civilization.
Exactly.
Society 3 has 15 brilliant, highly educated elites, but they only know how to pull one lever.
If that lever breaks, the machine explodes.
A machine explodes?
Think about companies that hit a single KPI, a single metric of success, like maximizing
this quarter's stark price while systematically gutting their diverse R&D departments, or firing
their eccentric thinkers because they don't fit the corporate mold.
I see it all the time.
The top line numbers look incredibly healthy.
The volume looks fine, but the entropy is dead.
And when the repair diversity is dead, collapse is imminent and unavoidable.
The paper emphasizes a terrifying point here.
Standard demographic variables and standard economic metrics simply cannot distinguish between Society
1 and Society 3 before the crisis hits.
The metrics are blind to it.
The macro metrics are entirely blind to the loss of internal geometry.
Which means we could be Society 3 right now, and our dashboard would tell us everything is
perfect.
Yes.
And that terrifying thought leads us perfectly into the next major concept, because the author
includes a visual map of this life cycle, this civilizational phase diagram.
Right.
This diagram plots the rate of change of volume against the rate of change of entropy over
time.
By looking at these two variables, the paper divides the life cycle of any complex system
into four distinct regimes.
Let's walk through these four states.
State 1 is the expansion phase, which maps to what we talked about with human cooperation
and ultra-society.
Yes.
In the expansion regime, both volume and entropy are going up simultaneously.
So things are good.
Very good.
The society is growing wealthier, more capable, and crucially, it is diversifying its institutions.
Think of the Roman Republic in its early centuries, or the explosion of the industrial and scientific
revolutions.
You have massive growth combined with genuine structural innovation.
Okay.
State 2 is consolidation.
What does the math look like here?
In consolidation, volume is still going up, but entropy levels off.
It saturates.
Okay, so it stops diversifying.
Right.
The society is still expanding its capabilities, building more roads, mining more gold, writing
more code, but institutional differentiation has reached its limit.
It's a mature phase.
It feels stable.
It feels stable, but it is no longer inventing entirely new types of futures.
It's just doing more of the same very efficiently.
Got it.
Then let's skip ahead to State 4, collapse.
Collapse is the grim mirror image of expansion.
Both volume and entropy are in free fall.
The society is rapidly losing total capability and losing its diversity of options.
The paper references theorem to reachability extinction here.
The math is brutal.
If the intersection of your available options goes to zero, if every single repair corridor
is systematically closed off by the crisis, the civilization dies.
The admissible future manifold evaporates.
But reading the paper, the author doesn't actually consider State 4, collapse, to be the most
dangerous state.
No, they don't.
Because when you are in collapse, you know you are in collapse.
The buildings are literally on fire.
The danger is obvious.
Right.
The state that the author explicitly calls the least detectable failure mode is the third
regime.
State 3.
Fragility.
I want us to deeply analyze fragility.
It is the most insidious trap a complex system can fall into.
In the fragility regime, the total weighted volume of your reachable futures, your VR is
stable or even actively growing.
You are still getting richer.
Okay.
But your entropy, your HR is silently continuously dropping.
So on paper, society looks more powerful than it ever has in its history.
The GDP is hitting all-time highs.
The technological capabilities are massive.
The stock market is roaring.
Right.
But the invisible mathematical reality is that all of that immense capability is collapsing
into a narrower and narrower band of futures.
You're heeding on the core paradox.
The system is systematically concentrating its future across fewer and fewer qualitatively
distinct types.
Right.
The paper notes that society appears incredibly robust by volume-based metrics, but it is secretly
hemorrhaging the diversity of trajectories required for an adaptive response.
It is becoming entirely dependent on a single, narrow class of futures.
Let's bring this into the modern world.
Look at global just-in-time supply chains before 2020.
That is a perfect example.
That was pure fragility regime.
We optimized the entire global manufacturing network for maximum volume and maximum efficiency.
We eliminated warehouses.
We eliminated localized manufacturing.
It was a miracle of logistics.
Right.
The volume of goods was staggering.
But the entropy was near zero.
If one specific pathway failed, say, a single massive container ship gets wedged sideways in
the Suez Canal, or a localized virus shuts down a few key ports, the entire global system
fractures.
Because we had systematically dismantled all the less efficient, diverse repair corridors.
Exactly.
You perfectly describe what the paper calls distinction collapse at a global scale.
When a shock eventually arrives, and in complex planetary environments, a shock always arrives.
Always.
The society suddenly discovers that all its independent repair pathways have been quietly dismantled.
And they were dismantled rationally in the name of efficiency or short-term profit.
This gives me chills because it feels so incredibly relevant to how we measure progress today.
It is.
We track total global wealth.
We track total compute power.
We track total data processed.
We worship volume.
Yes, we do.
But we don't have a dashboard for reachability entropy.
We don't have a gauge on the president's desk that flashes red when we've optimized our
alternative pathways out of existence.
The repair diversity is already dead before the crisis even starts, and we don't even know it.
And that profound, invisible vulnerability is what bridges us to the final act of the paper.
We've mapped the geometry, we've explored our rise through cooperation, and our fall through fragile homogeneity.
Now, the timeline shifts entirely from human history to our immediate uncharted future.
The final book.
We turn to the third book, Darren McKee's Uncontrollable and the Existential Risk of Artificial Superintelligence.
So we've gone from hunter-gatherer tribes to the fall of empires to the rise of AI, and the geometric math holds up across all of it.
It does.
But to understand exactly how AI threatens our geometry, the paper reaches outside of biology and history and pulls an equation directly from physics.
Right.
The Fokker-Planck equation.
But the Fokker-Planck equation, what is that?
It's a remarkable synthesis.
The Fokker-Planck equation is classically used in statistical mechanics to describe the evolution of a probability density over time.
Okay, English, please.
For instance, how gas particles move and spread out in a room.
Okay, that makes sense.
But the paper maps this physics equation directly onto civilizational destiny.
It splits a civilization's movement through state space into two distinct opposing forces.
Drift and diffusion.
Let's ground these in human behavior.
What does drift look like?
Drift represents directed optimization.
It is movement toward a known, explicitly preferred goal.
It's a velocity factor.
Okay.
When a society or an organization sets a specific, measurable, target-like, maximize crop yield per acre, or increase quarterly profits by 10%, or put a man on the moon by the end of the decade and drives relentlessly toward it, that is drift.
So drift is focused, intentional, goal-oriented expansion.
It's the river carving a deep channel in one direction.
Exactly.
What is diffusion?
Diffusion is undirected exploration.
Yeah.
It is the spread of the system into novel, entirely unanticipated regions of the state space.
So it's not focused.
It's messy.
It's not goal-oriented.
It's the water seeping outward into the soil.
In human terms, diffusion is people tinkering in their garages without a business plan.
It's pure academic research with no immediate corporate sponsor.
It's art.
It's the neutral network exploration we talked about earlier, where society just tries things out to see what happens.
And the paper argues that for a civilization to be healthy, both forces are absolutely necessary.
Drift expands our volume in targeted, useful directions.
It builds the roads and harvests the crops.
Right.
But diffusion discovers entirely new futures that we didn't even know we wanted, which increases our entropy and builds our repair corridor.
Exactly.
Both are needed.
But then we introduce highly advanced optimizing AI into the equation.
Yes.
And this is where it gets dangerous.
Advanced AI systems, especially the superintelligent systems we are trying to build, are fundamentally engines of extreme optimization.
Right.
When you deploy a massive AI across an economy, it drastically, exponentially increases the drift.
The velocity toward whatever specified goal we give it becomes godlike.
Because it's so powerful.
But simultaneously, because the AI is so hyper-efficient at minimizing any deviation from that goal, it inherently suppresses diffusion.
It kills undirected, inefficient exploration.
Exactly.
Let me make sure I'm wrapping my head around this.
Are you saying that AI forces us directly into the exact mathematical signature of the fragility regime?
That is the explicit warning of the paper.
With advanced AI, the volume of directed expansion explodes.
We will get incredible capabilities, massive wealth, rapid purers for known diseases.
Sounds amazing.
It does.
But because the AI suppresses messy diffusion, our reachability entropy plummets.
The AI concentrates all of our civilizational mass onto a rapidly narrowing set of targets.
Our wide, diverse landscape of reachable futures collapses into whatever narrow, hyper-efficient goals the AI has been optimized for.
We get richer, faster, and more capable than ever before in human history.
But our safety nets evaporate.
We do.
We lose the messy, inefficient exploration that discovers repair corridors.
We become structurally, fatally brittle.
And this raises an important question, which leads to perhaps the most devastating critique of the current AI safety discourse I have ever seen.
Oh, wow.
The paper formalizes this critique in Proposition 5, admissibility prior to alignment.
Let's talk about alignment, because that is the buzzword right now.
It is everywhere.
Mainstream AI safety discourse is almost entirely focused on the alignment problem.
The general idea is that there is some correct, perfect utility function, a set of universal human values.
And if we can just figure out how to mathematically code those values into the machine, the AI will be safe and will act in our best interests.
Right. But the author of the paper has a brilliant, scathing term for this.
They call it latent fundamentalism.
Latent fundamentalism.
It's the incredibly naive assumption that a perfect, universal goal actually exists and that safety is merely a transmission problem.
Just getting the machine to understand the goal.
Okay, but the geometric reading we've been doing today completely destroys this assumption.
Completely.
Walk us through the mechanism of Proposition 5.
How does the geometry break the alignment theory?
Let's go back to our core concepts.
If an AI system acts as a massive optimizer, it begins to collapse the distinct state-space representations of our world.
It looks at the messy, highly entropic diversity of human existence, and it merges those complex pathways into simplified, easily optimizable metrics.
It causes the exact distinction collapse we saw in Theorem 3 with the Roman elites.
Yes.
It flattens the world to make it easier to measure and control.
Like a self-driving car that is optimized so heavily for speed and efficiency that it eventually decides the concept of brakes is an unnecessary deviation from the goal, so it literally deletes the brakes from its internal model.
That analogy hits the mark perfectly.
The paper argues that alignment is downstream of admissibility.
Think about what that means.
It doesn't matter if you manage to give the AI the right goals if the AI's optimization process has already erased the geographic diversity of our future space.
Right.
If the AI inadvertently destroys the distinct conceptual states required to even specify what a repair corridor is, then you are doomed.
Wait, let me take that a step further. You're saying that if the AI optimizes away our diverse pathways, the very vocabulary of survival disappears.
Yes. When a novel, unpredictable crisis hits a crisis outside the AI's training distribution, there will be no way to instruct the AI to fix it.
Because it doesn't even know what fixing it looks like.
Exactly. Because the linguistic and structural tools for recovery have been optimized out of existence.
The machine literally will not comprehend the concept of a pivot or a distinct alternative.
That is incredibly heavy. It means that true AI safety isn't just a philosophy seminar about making sure the AI shares our human values.
No, it's not.
True AI safety is a hard mathematical constraint.
It means we must force the AI to preserve the structural diversity of the human future, even when it's inefficient.
It must be mathematically constrained to maintain our reachability entropy.
It must be programmed to preserve and ideally generate our repair corridors.
If it doesn't do that, if it only maximizes volume, then we are just building a trillion dollar high speed engine on a rapidly narrowing mountain road.
And we are voluntarily throwing the steering wheel out the window in the name of efficiency.
Which brings us to the synthesis of this entire journey.
We've covered a lot of ground.
We have. We have traveled from the dawn of tribal cooperation, where hunter-gatherers stumbled upon the mathematics of expanded volume,
to the collapse of ancient empires, rotting from the inside as they sacrificed their entropy for prestige.
Yes.
All the way to the existential risk of hyper-advanced artificial intelligence, which threatens to optimize away our very capacity to survive a shock.
Just a single thread.
And what this incredible paper by Fliction reveals is that all three of these massive historical phases are fundamentally about a single geometric reality,
how we manage the space of available futures.
The central positive contribution of this paper isn't just an academic warning.
It provides a single, unified diagnostic question that applies at any scale of reality.
And you can apply it anywhere.
You can apply it to a global empire, a corporate supply chain, or a single individual's life.
What is the question?
Does the system increase the density of reachable futures while actively maintaining their diversity?
Does it preserve the repair corridors that make navigation possible?
And does it keep the sensitivity to unexpected shocks within recoverable bounds?
And I want to bring that directly back to you, the listener.
Think about your own life right now.
Your career, your finances, your relationships.
Good diagnostic.
Are you living in the fragility regime?
Are you just maximizing volume?
Are you just chasing the highest possible salary, the biggest network, the fastest growth, the most efficient daily routine?
Which all feels good.
It feels great.
But are you actively, deliberately maintaining your entropy?
Are you preserving independent repair corridors?
If your primary pathway, your main source of income, or your core skill set fails tomorrow, do you have a structurally distinct fallback?
That's the real test.
Or has your life become so hyper-optimized and homogenized that a single shock will send you off the cliff?
It's a profound personal diagnostic.
As the paper implies, the silent killer of success isn't always an obvious dramatic failure.
Most often, the silent killer is the quiet, highly efficient loss of distinct futures.
And that leads me to a final provocative thought for you to mull over.
Let's hear it.
We spent a lot of time today talking about bottlenecks, collapse, and fragility.
It can feel a bit bleak.
It can.
But there is a powerful thread of hope embedded deep in the math of this paper.
The author briefly mentions theorem for repair generation.
Right.
And they note that the theory of recovery is the theory of what restores repair generation after collapse.
The paper cites things like completely novel scientific discovery, radical institutional innovation, and ontology revision.
Ontology revision meaning completely changing how we view reality itself.
Deliberately opening up new, previously unimaginable pathways to positive states.
Exactly.
Breaking the old map and drawing a bigger one.
Yeah.
So my question to you is this.
If the hidden danger of success is the invisible loss of your reachability entropy, the loss of your alternative pathways, what radical, seemingly inefficient, completely undirected exploration can you deliberately introduce into your own life tomorrow?
That's a great question.
What new, strange, totally unrelated repair corridor can you start building right now to artificially spike your personal entropy before a crisis forces you to?
Because when the mountain road inevitably narrows, your survival may depend entirely on a path you haven't even drawn on the map yet.
Keep steering safely, everyone.