So right now, the most popular cutting edge mathematical theory that we have, the one designed to explain the accelerating expansion of our universe, is mathematically off by exactly 57 orders of magnitude.
Yeah, which is just...
I mean, that's a 10 with 57 zeros behind it.
Uh-huh.
It's an error so incomprehensibly massive that it fundamentally breaks our entire understanding of reality.
Right. It's not a small rounding error.
No, not at all.
So welcome to the Deep Dive.
Today, we are looking at a brand new, incredibly dense 50-page paper by Flickshin, which was published literally today, March 17th, 2026.
I'm off the presses.
Exactly.
And the paper is titled, let me get this right, Constraints of Asymptotically Safe Quantum Gravity on Scalar Tensor Theories and Cosmic Strings.
Which is quite awful.
It really is.
But what this people does...
Is essentially take this mathematical duct tape that theoretical physicists have been using for the last decade to hold our broken cosmological models together, right?
Yeah.
And it takes that tape, throws it into the infinite heat of the Big Bang, and proves with just brutal mathematical rigor that the tape instantly disintegrates.
It really does.
I mean, it fundamentally changes how we are even allowed to build theories about the universe.
Right.
Because for decades, the theoretical physics community has operated under this sort of unwritten assumption.
The idea was that you can build a model that works for the low-energy universe we see in our telescopes today, right?
Uh-huh.
And then you can just sort of worry about how that model behaves at the microscopic infinite energy scale of the Big Bang later.
Like, we'll cross that bridge when we come to it.
Just kick the can down the road.
Exactly.
But this paper definitively shuts that door.
It demonstrates that the underlying quantum geometry of the universe acts as this incredibly ruthless structural filter.
Wow.
Yeah.
So if your theory cannot survive the extreme chaotic energies of the Planck scale, it is fundamentally mathematically forbidden from existing in our low-energy world today.
Okay, let's unpack this completely.
Yeah.
Because to really understand the gravity of this theoretical homicide, and it really is a homicide, we have to deeply understand the victim first.
Right.
The victim being the current state of modern cosmology.
Which is, frankly, in a state of unmitigated panic right now.
Total panic.
I mean, we've relied on the standard model of cosmology, what we call Lambda CDM, for decades.
Mm-hmm.
It's the framework built on cold, dark matter, which is the scaffolding holding galaxy.
Right.
And then you have Lambda, the cosmological constant, which represents the static vacuum energy of empty space just pushing the universe apart.
But Lambda CDM is currently fracturing under the weight of two massive observational crises.
It's not looking good for Lambda CDM.
No, it's really not.
And the most famous of these, of course, is the Hubble tension.
Oh, the Hubble tension.
That is the nightmare that wakes cosmologists up in a cold.
Seriously.
I mean, it's a fundamental disagreement about the current expansion rate of the universe, which we denote as H0.
Right.
Yeah.
We have these two highly refined, incredibly precise methodologies to measure this rate, and they are yielding fiercely incompatible results.
Completely different numbers.
Exactly.
So the first method relies on the late-time local universe.
We build what's called a copy.
Cosmic distance ladder.
Right.
Using the standard candles.
Yeah.
Exactly.
We look at cepheid variable stars.
These are pulsating stars.
And the period of their pulsation is directly linked to their intrinsic luminosity.
Henrietta Swan Leavitt figured that out over a century ago, I think.
Yes, she did.
It was a brilliant discovery.
Because by comparing their true brightness to how dim they appear to us, we get a precise distance.
Got it.
And then we calibrate those against type E supernovae, which are thermonuclear explosions of white dwarfs.
And they always detonate at a very highly specific mass limit, the Chandrasekhar limit.
So they always have the same brightness.
It's the astronomical equivalent of knowing exactly how bright a 100-watt light bulb is.
Right.
Like a great way to put it.
So when you see one down the street, you can measure its apparent dimness and calculate exactly how many feet away it is.
Precisely.
And when we use these standard candles to measure the local universe, we get a relatively high expansion rate.
But then, we use a completely separate early universe methodology.
We look at the cosmic microwave background, or the CMB.
Right, the CMB, the afterglow of the Big Bang.
Exactly.
It's the remnant thermal radiation from the epoch of recombination.
That's when the universe cooled just enough for protons and electrons.
To form neutral hydrogen.
Which finally let photons travel freely, right?
Right, the fog lifted.
Now, the CMB isn't perfectly uniform.
It has these microscopic temperature fluctuations.
Little speckles we see in those famous maps.
Yeah, those speckles.
And those are actually the frozen imprint of baryon acoustic oscillations.
Wait, baryon acoustic meaning sound waves?
Yeah, literal sound waves that propagated through the primordial plasma of the early universe.
That's so wild.
That's so wild to think about, sound waves in the Big Bang.
It is wild.
And by measuring the angular scale of those acoustic peaks, we establish a sound horizon.
It's essentially a standard ruler for the early cosmos.
Okay, so a standard ruler instead of a standard candle.
Right.
We then take that early universe ruler, feed it into the lambda-CDM mathematical machinery,
and we fast forward 13.8 billion years to predict,
what the expansion rate should be today.
And this is where the crisis erupts.
Oh, yeah.
Because when you fast forward that CMB data using the standard math,
the predicted expansion rate is significantly slower than what we actually measure locally with the standard candles.
It's way off.
And as this new paper highlights, this is not just some marginal discrepancy.
We are looking at a tension greater than four sigma.
Yeah, four sigma is huge.
Just to put that in context for you listening,
in particle physics and cosmology,
a four sigma discrepancy means there is roughly a one in 15,000 chance
that this difference is merely a statistical artifact.
Right, meaning it's almost certainly not a mistake in the data.
It strongly implies new physics.
Exactly.
And the Hubble tension isn't acting alone, is it?
No.
It has a partner in crime, the sigma-8 tension.
Right.
This relates to the amplitude of matter density fluctuations.
Basically, how clumpy the universe is.
How clumpy?
Yeah.
Lambda-CDM, when it's calibrated to that early CMB data,
predicts a universe where matter should cluster together at a very specific rate
to form galaxies and massive superclusters.
Okay.
But when we actually survey the late-time universe using weak gravitational lensing,
which is measuring the cosmic shear,
you know, those tiny distortions in the shape,
the shapes of background galaxies caused by the gravitational pull of foreground dark matter,
we find that the universe is notably smoother.
Yeah.
It's less clumpy than the theory predicts.
Okay, so our standard model is over-predicting the clustering of matter
and it's under-predicting the speed of the expansion.
Exactly.
Like we said, it's a house with a fundamentally cracked foundation.
A very expensive, heavily researched house.
Right.
And theoretical physicists, in their attempt,
to save this framework without throwing out decades of progress,
they developed a highly sophisticated workaround.
Yeah, they did.
They introduced dynamical dark energy.
Right.
This idea that lambda isn't a constant at all.
Exactly.
Instead of a constant, it's an evolving dynamic scalar field
that changes its behavior over cosmic time.
So, if dark energy was fundamentally different in the early universe than it is today,
you could say that it's not.
Right.
You could theoretically bend the expansion history
to make the CMB data neatly match the local supernova data.
Which leads us directly to the specific class of theories
that this new paper absolutely destroys.
Right.
Let's get into that.
To make dynamical dark energy work without violating a host of other physical laws,
theorists converged on this highly popular mathematical framework.
The Horn-Desky models.
Yes.
Specifically, shift-symmetric horn-desky models.
The Horn-Desky scalar tensor theories.
And within that, models that utilize a mechanism called kinetic braiding.
Okay.
I want to dive deep into kinetic braiding here.
Because physicists absolutely love this framework right now.
They do.
It's been the darling of cosmology for a while.
And it all stems from this deep mathematical terror of spawning what are called Ostrogrotsky ghosts.
Right?
Yeah.
Nobody wants ghosts in their equations.
Right.
So, whenever theorists try to...
...modify Einstein's general relativity by adding new dynamic scalar fields
with higher derivative equations to explain dark energy,
they almost inevitably trigger this Ostrogrotsky instability.
Yeah.
Which goes way back.
Mikhail Ostrogrotsky proved a theorem back in 1850 regarding classical mechanics.
1850?
Yeah.
He showed that if you have a Lagrangian,
which is a mathematical function that summarizes the dynamics of a system,
and that Lagrangian depends on time derivatives higher than the first order without degeneracies,
the Hamiltonian of that system becomes unbounded from below.
Okay.
Unbounded from below.
What does that mean in practical terms?
In the context of quantum field theory, it translates to the creation of ghost particles.
These are excitations that possess negative kinetic energy.
Which is mathematically catastrophic for the universe.
Simultaneously catastrophic.
Because if a particle...
If a particle has negative kinetic energy, the faster it moves, the less energy it has.
So if a ghost particle were to interact with a normal particle in the vacuum of space,
the normal particle would gain positive energy and accelerate.
Exactly.
And the ghost would gain negative energy and also accelerate.
Yeah, they would infinitely accelerate each other.
They'd just instantly extract infinite energy from the vacuum.
The universe would effectively explode into a chaotic soup,
eventually.
Infinite radiation in a fraction of a second.
A very bad day for the universe.
Right.
So obviously, theories that predict ghosts are immediately thrown out.
Exactly.
The Ostergradsky ghost is the ultimate theoretical taboo.
And that is why Gregory Horndesky's work from 1974 is so incredibly revered.
What did Horndesky do?
He mathematically mapped out the absolute most general scalar tensor theorem
in the theory of gravity in four dimensions that leads strictly to second-order equations of motion.
Ah, keeping it to second order.
Right.
By keeping the equation second order,
he proved you could fundamentally modify gravity and introduce these complex scalar fields
while mathematically guaranteeing that no Ostergradsky ghost would ever be spawned.
So he basically built a mathematical safe zone.
Exactly.
It is the definitive safe zone for building cosmological models.
And within that Horndesky safe zone,
we get this incredibly elegant trick called kinetic braiding.
Right.
Because instead of just dropping a dark energy field into the universe
and letting it exist independently,
kinetic braiding tangles the kinetic energy of this new scalar field
directly into the Einstein tensor.
Yeah, the mathematical object that describes the curvature of space-time itself.
Right.
So it links the expansion of the universe intrinsically
to the motion of the scalar field.
It allows the dark energy to dynamically adapt.
Which resolves the Hubble tension,
matches the expansion history,
and avoids the ghosts.
I mean, it is a masterpiece of phenomenological engineering.
It is brilliant phenomenological engineering.
But, you know, it is precisely that phenomenology.
Right.
It is a bottom-up construction
designed entirely to fit the low-energy data we observe today.
Just fitting the data.
To the telescope.
Exactly.
And as the author of this new paper points out,
these Horndesky models completely ignore
the great lingering nightmare of modern theoretical physics.
The ultraviolet or UV problem.
Right.
Because general relativity,
and by extension these Horndesky modifications,
completely break down mathematically at the Planck scale
around 10 to the 19 GV.
Okay, we have to really explore this briefly.
Okay.
Because it's not just a matter of the math getting a little fuzzy.
No, it's a total mathematical disintegration.
It comes down to perturbative non-renormalizability.
Right.
In quantum field theory,
the way we calculate how particles interact
is through perturbation theory.
We calculate the simplest interaction,
then we add the probability of more complex interactions
involving virtual particles popping in and out of the vacuum.
Those are the quantum loop corrections.
Right, the loops.
And this works flawlessly for the other fundamental forces.
It really does.
I mean, in quantum electrodynamics, QED,
which describes electromagnetism,
you also encounter mathematical infinities
when you calculate these loop corrections.
Yeah, and infinities pop up there, too.
But in the late 1940s,
physicists like Feynman, Schwinger, and Tominaga
figured out a way to absorb those infinities.
Renormalization.
Exactly.
Because the coupling constant of electromagnetism,
the fine structure constant, is dimensionless.
Okay.
Since it lacks a mass dimension,
you only need to redefine a finite number of parameters,
like the mass and charge of the electron,
to absorb all the infinities at every level of perturbation.
So you just go to a lab, you measure those few parameters,
plug them back into the theory,
and the theory gives you exquisitely perturbative
precise, finite predictions.
The most precise predictions in all of science, actually.
But gravity fundamentally resists this process.
Yeah, it throws a wrench in the whole thing.
And it all traces back to Newton's gravitational constant, g,
because in the natural units used by particle physicists,
where the speed of light and Planck's constant are set to one,
g is not dimensionless.
Right.
It actually has a negative mass dimension,
specifically a mass dimension of negative two.
And that negative dimension acts like a mathematical virus
when you try to calculate quantum loops at high energies.
It dictates how the divergences scale.
Because g has a dimension of negative two.
Every single time you add an additional quantum loop to your calculation
to get a more precise answer,
the degree of the mathematical divergence increases.
The infinity gets worse.
Exactly.
So to cancel out a worse infinity,
you have to introduce a brand new mathematical counterterm.
Okay.
And then you calculate the next loop,
and you get an even worse infinity requiring another new counterterm.
And it just never stops.
Never terminates.
Yeah.
To make general relativity mathematically sound at the Planck scale
using perturbation theory,
you must introduce an infinite number of counterterms.
Which means you require an infinite number of free parameters.
Yep.
And if a theory,
has an infinite number of parameters that you have to go out and physically measure
before the theory can make a single prediction,
while the theory has exactly zero predictive power,
it's completely useless.
It's essentially the universe's way of telling us that our mathematical framework
is fundamentally the wrong language for describing reality at that scale.
A theory that blows up into infinite uncontrolled parameters at high energy
isn't a fundamental,
fundamental description of nature.
It's merely an effective field theory.
It's a low resolution placeholder that only works when things are cold and slow.
Which leads us to the critical turning point of this paper.
Yes.
Because if your dark energy model,
your highly prized,
Horn-Desky kinetic braiding,
is based on a framework that disintegrates into infinite nonsense at the Big Bang.
Yeah.
How can it possibly be the true,
fundamental mechanism governing the universe?
Right.
It can't.
Exactly.
For decades,
the dominant theoretical response to this UV problem
was just to abandon quantum field theory entirely at the Planck scale and adopt string theory.
Right.
String theory.
The idea that particles aren't points,
but one-dimensional vibrating strings existing in higher dimensional space-time.
Yeah.
Which smears out the interactions and cures the infinities.
But string theory has its own massive force.
But string theory has its own massive force. But string theory has its own massive force.
Primarily the lack of any experimental evidence for these extra dimensions or string excitations.
We haven't seen anything.
We haven't seen supersymmetry at the Large Hadron Collider.
And the mathematical landscape of string theory is notoriously difficult to constrain.
It's a mess.
So if we want to solve the UV problem without inventing extra dimensions and vibrating strings,
we have to turn to the core mechanism of today's deep dive.
Asymptotic safety.
Yes, asymptotic safety.
This was an idea first floated by the legendary physicist Steven Weinberg during his 1979 Arise lectures.
And it is a breathtakingly elegant proposition.
It really is.
Yeah.
Weinberg's profound insight was that, well, perhaps we don't need to throw away quantum field theory.
Okay.
You see, the problem of perturbative non-renormalizability assumes that as energy increases,
the coupling constants run away to infinity, which requires infinite counterterms.
Right.
But Weinberg suggested that if we analyze gravity using non-perturbative methods,
we might find that the coupling constants don't run to infinity at all.
Wait, really?
Yeah.
Instead, as the energy scale approaches the Planck limit, the couplings might just hit a mathematical ceiling.
They might asymptotically approach what he called a non-Gaussian fixed point.
Okay.
But Weinberg did deeply examine the mechanics of this non-Gaussian fixed point,
because this is effectively the theoretical bouncer of our universe.
The bouncer, exactly.
And the foundation of this idea relies on the renormalization group, or RG flow.
Right. RG flow.
Ken Wilson revolutionized physics in the 1970s by changing how we think about renormalization.
He showed that it isn't just a mathematical trick to hide infinities, right?
It's actual physics.
process of integrating out high-energy momentum shells. So as you change the
energy scale you are looking at, the physical laws, the coupling constants,
literally flow and change values. They morph. And the primary mathematical
instrument that physicists use today to calculate this flow and hunt for
Weinberg's fixed point is the functional renormalization group. The FRG.
Specifically, the Wetterich equation, formulated by Christoph Wetterich in
1993. Okay. Conceptually, the Wetterich equation tracks the evolution of the
effective average action of the universe. It introduces a momentum scale, which is
typically denoted as K, and an infrared regulator function, or subscript K. And
this regulator acts like a mathematical sieve. A mathematical sieve, exactly. Right, so
it suppresses quantum fluctuations below the
energy scale K, but it leaves the high- energy fluctuations above K fully active.
Yep. So as you slide the scale K from infinity all the way down to zero, you are
methodically, step-by-step integrating out the quantum mechanical weirdness of
the universe. You're moving from the microscopic quantum realm to the
macroscopic classical reality we observe today. And the Wetterich equation gives
you a precise
vector field on what we call theory space right theory space this is an abstract infinite
dimensional geometric space where every single point represents a complete distinct physical
theory with its own specific values for gravity electromagnetism dark energy couplings all of it
it's the map of all possible physics right and the rg flow describes a trajectory a continuous curve
through this infinite dimensional landscape it shows how the universe evolves as you change the
scale and the uv fixed point weinberg safe zone is a highly specific point in this theory space
where the beta functions which dictate how fast the couplings change all simultaneously hit exactly
zero so the flow just stop it stops yeah the universe achieves a state of ultimate scale
invariance
wow
, if gravity possesses this non-gaussian fixed point then the theory is asymptotically safe
it is protected from the infinities of the planck scale but the true power of asymptotic
safety isn't just that it saves the math is it no not at all it's how it violently
restricts the possible physics of the low energy universe and this comes down to the
critical distinction between relevant and irrelevant couplings this is the exact mechanism
politiching uses in the paper to tear down the horn desky models right the bouncer in action exactly
when you analyze the mathematical behavior of the rg flow exactly at the uv fixed point you can
linearize the flow equations to see how the couplings behave if you nudge them slightly away
from the point this yields a set of critical exponents and based on these exponents every
single physical coupling in the universe is strictly calculated by the flow of the couplings
and this is categorized as either relevant or irrelevant and we really have to clarify this
naming convention for you listening because irrelevant sounds like a parameter that just
doesn't matter and can be safely ignored it's a terrible name obviously it really is because in
the context of the renormalization group an irrelevant coupling is actually the most dominant
restrictive inescapable prediction a theory can make absolutely let's look at the mechanics of why
irrelevant coupling has a positive critical exponent this means that as you lower the
energy scale flowing away from the big bang down to our macroscopic world
the relevant coupling is repelled away from the fixed point it diverges wildly right and because
it is repelled a relevant coupling can end up possessing a wide array of completely different
numerical values in the infrared it could be anything it depends entirely on its exact microscopic structure.
on its exact microscopic starting condition in the deep uv the mathematics of the fixed point
cannot predict what his low energy value will be therefore it remains a free parameter we as
experimentalists are forced to go out and measure it in a laboratory or with a telescope to determine
its value in our specific universe but an irrelevant coupling has a negative critical
exponent it is mathematically attracted to the fixed point as you go to higher energies
which means conversely as you flow down to lower energies the irrelevant coupling is
relentlessly pulled onto a singular rigid mathematical trajectory it completely loses
its memory of whatever initial conditions it might have had exactly it forgets everything
by the time the flow reaches our macroscopic scale the value of an irrelevant coupling
is absolutely dictated by the quantum geometry of the fixed point we don't measure it to find
out what it is the theory explicitly predicts its exact value and here is where the trap snaps
shut on horn desky okay if a coupling is categorized as irrelevant by asymptotic safety
and the universe dictates it must have a value of exactly zero right but our phenomenological
dark energy model requires it to have a value of 10 million to fix the hubble tension then the
dark energy model is instantly dead dead on arrival it is fundamentally incompatible with
the quantum structure of space-time this mechanism acts as an incredibly potent predictive funnel
and the paper draws a really fascinating deep connection here to information geometry
specifically section 12.4 yes it maps this entire rg flow process to non-equilibrium
thermodynamics the paper explores the fischer information metric which is a way of measuring
the distance or distinguishability between different probability distributions right
and it turns out this sliding from infinite energy down to our scale isn't just a change
in numbers it is a fundamental irreversible coarse graining of physics it is deeply analogous to
perilman's ritchie flow oh the math used to solve the poincare conjecture the
very first point of the point of the point of the point of the point of the point of the point of
the very same gregory perilman used the ritchie flow which takes a complex irregular geometric
manifold and mathematically allows it to evolve over a parameter akin to time it smooths out all
the extreme curvatures until it reaches a highly symmetric geometry perilman demonstrated that
this smoothing process is governed by an entropy-like functional hole that monotonically
increases so as the universe zooms out
from the microscopic chaos of the planck scale the intricate high energy quantum fluctuations
are systematically averaged out they're blurred away exactly information about the ultimate
microscopic state of reality is permanently lost to the macroscopic observer the universe
is fundamentally blurring its own image right and the fixed points those uv starting lines
represent states of maximum entropy compatible with the underlying symmetries of the theory
so this entropic flow fundamentally explains the predictive power of irrelevant couplings yes it
does if you imagine theory space as a massive hyperdimensional topographical landscape the
relevant couplings are like these vast flat planes where water can pool in any number of
configurations but the irrelevant couplings are the steep inescapable valleys the macroscopic
laws of physics we experience are essentially the water that has flowed down
those entropic valleys the thermodynamic loss of information forces the universe into highly specific
rigid manifestations that paints an incredibly beautiful yet sort of fatalistic picture of the
laws of physics the chaos of the big bang is forcefully channeled into order by the sheer
geometry of theory space it really is beautiful so we now have the crisis lambda cdm feeling
and horn dusky kinetic braiding stepping in to save it and we have our framework asymptotic safety
the wetterich equation and the rigid predictive funnel of irrelevant couplings now we apply the
framework to the theory right this is the horn dusky teardown the paper aims the functional
renormalization group directly at the specific mathematical couplings that define kinetic
braiding and the mathematical teardown focuses sharply on the two operators that are absolutely
essential for the kinetic braiding mechanism to function as a viable dark energy candidate okay
what are they first we have the cubic braiding coupling which the author denotes as h this
operator is the physical heart of the model it is the term that explicitly couples the scalar
field's kinetic energy to the curvature of space-time that's the braid that's the braid
yeah secondly there is the quartic coupling denoted as g
which dictates the self-interaction strength of the scalar dark energy field
let's start by looking at what the bottom-up phenomenological models
actually demand of these couplings okay because if you want kinetic braiding to successfully
drive the accelerated expansion of the universe today mimic a dynamical cosmological constant
and bend the expansion history just enough to elegantly resolve the hubble
tension well the math dictates that the self-interaction coupling g must be massive it
has to be huge the paper notes that in natural units g must be on the order of nine times ten to
the seventh inverse electron volts to the fourth power right it must be an incredibly dominant
force in the late universe so that phenomenological requirement is the target
the paper then takes these operators constructs the effective average action for the shift
symmetric horn desky theory
and runs it through the rhetoric equation to find the uv fixed point
and what happens what emerges from the complex trace calculations is a shifted gaussian fixed
point or sgfp sgp at this specific fixed point gravity and the scalar field interact
but the fundamental nature of the mathematical operators is revealed
and the braiding coupling h encounters an insurmountable mathematical barrier which is the
z2 kinetic symmetry oh we need to dissect this z2 symmetry because this is the specific weapon that
kills the model it is the murder weapon in the core lagrangian of this theory of the basic kinetic
term for the scalar field involves the square of its derivative essentially d phi squared right
because the field is squared if you perform a mathematical transformation where you flip the
sign of the entire field-changing phi to negative phi you're going to be able to find the z2 kinetic
symmetry of the scalar field and if we do that over and over again when you have the negative phi
everywhere in the universe the negative signs just cancel out negative times negative is positive
exactly the fundamental kinetic energy of the system remains completely unchanged and invariant
that is the z2 symmetry it is a fundamental property of the core theory but the cubic
braiding term the h operator is structurally different right it involves three derivatives of
the scalar field interacting with space-time curvature
It roughly takes the form of d phi squared times the box operator of phi.
Okay. Three derivatives.
Because there is an odd number of field operators interacting in that specific term,
if you apply that same Z2 transformation and flip phi to negative phi.
The H term does not cancel out.
Exactly. It actively flips its own sign.
The braiding operator fundamentally breaks the Z2 kinetic symmetry of the underlying framework.
And the strict, unforgiving rules of quantum field theory state that if a specific operator breaks a discrete symmetry
that the rest of the quantum action preserves its beta function,
the equation dictating how that coupling flows with energy must strictly factorize.
That's the rule.
The paper calculates the explicit beta function for the braiding coupling, beta sub H.
And the mathematical structure of the result is just devastating.
It really is.
The function factors out the H coupling itself.
It takes the form of beta sub H equals H multiplied by a massive, complex bracket of other gravitational interactions.
And the fact that H is a direct linear multiplier of the entire beta function
means that H equals zero is an exact permanent solution to the flow equation.
Because zero times anything is zero.
Exactly.
If H starts at zero, the beta function is zero, meaning H never changes.
This is the definition.
This is the definition of a coupling being symmetry protected.
Wow.
The strict geometry of the shifted Gaussian fixed point mathematically proves that exactly at the UV limit,
the braiding coupling H must be absolutely zero.
But could the flow of the universe as it cools down somehow generate the braiding?
I mean, we established earlier that irrelevant couplings are drawn to the fixed point in the UV and repelled in the IR.
Does H grow as we move to the macroscopic scale?
No.
And this is the fatal blow.
The paper calculates the critical exponent for H at the fixed point.
And it confirms that H is an irrelevant coupling.
Ah, the funnel.
Remember the predictive funnel.
Because it is irrelevant, its macroscopic value is entirely dictated by its UV value.
Right.
Since the UV value is symmetry protected to be exactly zero,
the irrelevant flow locks it at zero for the entire history of the universe.
It never grows.
Never.
The macroscopic low energy value of the kinetic braiding coupling is mathematically forced to be zero.
The quantum fluctuations of gravity simply cannot radiatively generate an operator that violates the Z2 symmetry from nothing.
So the fundamental mechanism of Horn-Desky dark energy is completely erased.
The braiding is dead.
But the theoretical carnage isn't over.
What happens to the other crucial parameter, the quartic self-interaction coupling G?
Right, the one that needs to be massive.
The one that needs to be in 9 times 10 to the 7th to solve the Hubble tension.
Does it suffer the same symmetry protected fate?
Interestingly, no.
The G coupling involves four scalar fields interacting.
An even number.
Okay, so it survives the flip.
Exactly.
Flipping phi to negative phi preserves the operator.
It does not break the Z2 symmetry.
Because it respects the symmetry, the beta function for G does not strictly factorize in the same way.
Okay.
When the researchers calculate the flow, they find that G is heavily influenced by gravitational anti-screening.
Let's visualize gravitational anti-screening because that's an important concept.
Sure.
Okay.
loops interact with the scalar field and actively drive the coupling away from zero at the fixed
point precisely the graviton fluctuations force the fixed point value of g to be non-zero okay
the paper tracks this non-zero value categorizes g as an irrelevant coupling once again and flows
it all the way down the entropic valleys to the macroscopic cosmic scale and what's the number
the exact prediction generated by asymptotic safety for the late time universe is that the
quartic coupling g should have a value of approximately 10 to the negative seventh and
there's the kill shot yep because the top-down fundamental math of quantum gravity dictates that
g must be 10 to the negative seven yeah but the phenomenological bottom-up models designed to
match telescope data and fix the hubble tension
you
absolutely require g to be nine times ten to the positive seven right we are looking at a
mathematical chasm of 57 orders of magnitude between the fundamental structure of the universe
and the dark energy models we've invented it is difficult to overstate how catastrophic
a 57 order of magnitude discrepancy is in physics i'm going to use an analogy here just once to
anchor this scale for you listening it is the equivalent of
absolutely required g to be nine times ten to the positive seven right we are looking at a
mathematical chasm of 57 orders of magnitude between the fundamental structure of the universe
asking a contractor to build a tiny one inch wooden foot bridge across a puddle in your driveway
that one inch represents the 10 to the negative seventh value predicted by quantum gravity
but instead of building a one inch plank the contractor builds a bridge that spans the entire
observable width of the universe and then squares that distance wow that unimaginable universe
spanning hyper structure represents the entire observable width of the universe and then squares
the nine times ten to the positive seventh value required by the horn desky models it's just absurd
it's not a parameter that can be tweaked you cannot adjust a dial in the math to bridge a gap of 57 zeros
it is a fundamental refutation of the concept and the consequences for the cosmological equations are
terminal the paper takes these strict asymptotic safety predictions the h equals zero and the g is
roughly ten to the negative seven and the h equals zero and the g is roughly ten to the negative seven
seven and plugs them back into the friedman equations which govern the expansion of the
universe exactly when you calculate the energy density of the scalar field under these new
constraints the math yields a negative energy density which completely inverts the physical
reality of dark energy entirely dark energy must possess a positive energy density and a negative
pressure to drive the accelerated expansion of the space-time fabric
scalar field with a negative energy density would cause the universe to decelerate and eventually
collapse it fundamentally fails to describe the cosmos we inhabit so the conclusion drawn in
section 4.6 of the paper is definitive any attempt to resolve the hubble tension by employing shift
symmetric kinetic braiding within the framework of a uv complete quantum gravity theory is
mathematically impossible the structural filter the
planck scale absolutely forbids it if cosmologists wish to solve the hubble crisis they must
completely abandon this class of phenomenological theories the horn desky duct tape has been
incinerated it really is back to the drawing board for dark energy that is a profound shift
in the theoretical landscape but the paper doesn't stop at dismantling dark energy does
it no but it has another target it pivots its mathematical artillery toward the early universe
specifically targeting the existence of topological defects which brings us to the
second major casualty of this deep dive cosmic strings cosmic strings now cosmic strings are
theoretically fascinating artifacts to understand them we have to look at the
symmetry breaking events that occurred fractions of a second after the big bang right as the
primordial universe expanded it cooled rapidly undergoing massive phase transitions this is often
analyzed through the kibble mechanism it compares the early universe to the process of water
freezing into ice or a metal cooling below its curie temperature to become ferromagnetic right
because when water freezes the crystalline structure of the ice doesn't form perfectly
uniformly across the entire volume at exactly the same time right different regions freeze
with different alignments and where these misaligned regions meet you get visible cracks
or domain boundaries in the ice exactly and in the extreme environment of the early universe
when fundamental energetic symmetries spontaneously broke the mathematical fields defining reality
could also become misaligned so where these distinct domains of space-time met the trapped
energy would form one-dimensional topological defects these defects are the cosmic strings
they would be unimaginably
thin thinner than a fundamental particle but carrying a colossal mass energy density
a single meter of a cosmic string could weigh as much as an entire continent or even a planet yeah
and they would stretch across the entire observable universe forming vast chaotic networks just
oscillating and whipping through space-time at relativistic speeds and the cleanest most standard
mathematical method for generating these strings in theoretical physics is a framework known as the
abelian higgs model right it involves a u1 gauge theory coupled to a complex scalar field the
dynamics of this field are governed by a specific potential famously shaped like a mexican hat the
famous mexican hat potentially at immense temperatures the scalar field sits perfectly
at the symmetric peak of the hat but as the universe cools we're unable to predict gonna get
When the universe cools, that state becomes unstable, and the field rolls down into the circular valley at the brim, spontaneously breaking the U1 symmetry.
And the trap-winding numbers in this phase transition give birth to the strings.
So physicists have been searching the heavens for observational evidence of these strings for decades.
They really have.
Because they are so massive and move so violently, they would constantly be shedding energy in the form of gravitational waves.
A network of cosmic strings would produce a persistent, stochastic background hum of gravitational waves permeating the entire cosmos.
And recently, the observational data regarding this hum has become incredibly precise, primarily due to the Nanograv 15-year dataset.
Nanograv is one of the most brilliant observational experiments in modern astronomy.
It really is genius.
Because instead of building a detector,
they monitor a vast array of millisecond pulsars, rapidly spinning, highly magnetized neutron stars that emit beams of radiation with the precision of an atomic clock.
By constantly measuring the arrival times of these pulses across dozens of pulsars,
they can detect the minute stretching and squeezing of space-time between Earth and the pulsars caused by passing gravitational waves.
They look for a specific...
A specific spatial correlation signature known as the Helling's-Downs curve.
And in their 15-year dataset, Nanograv successfully detected this stochastic gravitational wave background.
They found the hum.
However, the spectral shape and amplitude of the hum they detected placed severe upper bounds on the properties of hypothetical cosmic strings.
Right, the data dictates that if the Abelian-Higgs model is correct,
the symmetry-breaking system will be able to detect these pulsars.
Right, the data dictates that if the Abelian-Higgs model is correct, the symmetry-breaking system will be able to detect these pulsars.
The scale, which determines the tension and mass of the cosmic strings,
must be strictly lower than 4.6 times 10 to the 14th GeV.
Okay, 4.6 times 10 to the 14th.
Yes.
If the strings were any heavier or more energetic than that,
they would have produced a gravitational wave signal significantly louder and different than what Nanograv observed.
So, observationally, we have a hard ceiling, roughly 10 to the 14th GeV.
Yes.
If we sensitively mount until the
constructed
While we know he has
the brain in his hands,
it has no connection to
the derived
neural network.
So, for example, if-
the u1 gauge coupling independently of gravity okay as you flow the energy scale upwards towards
the big bang the gauge coupling exhibits what is known as a lando pole a lando pole the interaction
strength grows unconditionally driven by the quantum fluctuations of the scalar field until
it mathematically diverges to infinity at a finite energy scale so without gravity the theory destroys
itself before it ever reaches the planck scale the mass just blows up but as we established
the universe possesses gravity so the researchers fold the gravitational fluctuations back into the
wetterjik equation to see how space-time curvature affects the string and remarkably gravity exerts a
stabilizing force really yes the graviton loops enter the beta function for the gauge coupling
with a negative sign they provide a massive
anti-gravity function for the gauge coupling with a negative sign they provide a massive
anti-screening effect that directly opposes the runaway growth caused by the scalar field okay so
the gravitons fight back exactly this gravitational drag is strong enough to completely neutralize the
lando pole the gauge coupling is forced into an interacting finite non-gaussian fixed point
gravity mathematically rescues the cosmic strings from oblivion well it seems like a triumph for the
theory
gravity saves the strings but this is quantum gravity and salvation comes with an incredibly
steep ultimately fatal cost the mathematical cost of that gravitational anti-screening is profound
what happened the fixed point structure fundamentally alters the trajectory of
the scalar field's potential to maintain the stability of that mexican hat potential
all the way down from the planck scale to the macroscopic universe the symmetry breaking scale
the tension of the strings is forced to track the plank mass oh no the asymptotic safety framework
explicitly calculates that the cosmic string tension must be generated at approximately 10 to
the 19th yeah let's compare the ledgers here the nanograph telescope data firmly establishes that
the string tension absolutely cannot exceed 10 to the 14th chef the fundamental top-down quantum
gravity math dictates that the string tension if it reaches the greeding forcing it up above the
nauticalunde strength it become known as the gain small area by which it sets the load of gravity and
tension must be 10 to the 19th jivy that is an overproduction of more than four orders of
magnitude the strings produced by the pristine abelian higgs model are mathematically required
to be tens of thousands of times too heavy and energetic to exist in our observed universe
the pure theory and the observational reality are in violent disagreement they really are however
theoretical physicists are remarkably tenacious that's true if the standard model produces
strings that are too heavy the standard procedure is to modify the model the paper details the
precise mathematical lengths to which theorists must go to artificially drag that 10 to the 19th
planck scale tension down to the 10 to the 14th observational limit so to change the tension you
have to fundamentally alter the beta functions
you have to fundamentally alter the beta functions
governing the rg flow you have to introduce a new source of mathematical drag to counteract the
overwhelming power of the graviton loops right and in quantum field theory the way you generate
that specific type of negative drag is by introducing fermions because while bosonic
loops like those of gravitons or scalar fields typically drive couplings in one direction
fermionic loops inherently carry a negative sign in their quantum field
theoretically what happens here is that there's no
d- billions but every time you raise the duration to aiete in aylene there's a contradiction
that comes out at
n my'
z k
which is that
on the power of the higher
must be the voltage quantity
of forces
n
model of particle physics and injecting them into the early universe strictly to fix the math of the
cosmic strings yes that's the fix the paper performs a rigorous exhaustive stability analysis
of the scalar potential to determine exactly how much fermionic screening is required
how many new fundamental particles must we add to reality to make this work the mathematical
requirement is staggering how many to generate enough screening to drag the tension down to the
nanograv limit while simultaneously ensuring that the scalar potential remains fundamentally stable
and doesn't collapse into a false vacuum state across the entire cosmological evolution of the
universe the equations demand the introduction of at least 42 extra highly specific direct fermions
42 42
it is darkly comedic that the answer to saving this universal model is literally 42 douglas adams
would be proud he really would but physically this is what the paper refers to as an extreme
complexity tax it's a huge tax we are trying to explain a relatively simple topological defect
a crack in the cosmic ice but to justify its existence within a uv complete theory we are
mathematically forced to bloat the fundamental theory of the universe and to justify its existence
we are mathematically forced to bloat the fundamental theory of the universe and to justify
its existence within a canonical continental particle physics of the
to justify its existence within a canonical continental particle physics of the universe
universe to an utterly unrecognizable degree exactly it is the equivalent of
going to a diner for a simple five-dollar meal but the mathematical laws of the transaction
difficult to put into yani even a range
even a range so far exactly 42 solid gold bars the computing does no damage it just validates the receipt
absolutely legit even if that 아까 klaussmann's
absurd entirely unjustified theoretical cost an abstract짜olda
ondo
explain a concept of quantity trees and floor typesetting
and this leads to a brilliant unifying conclusion in this section of the paper
this leads in this section of the paper
which of course seems produces a Ef object
the top-down quantum gravity math imposing this ridiculous 42 fermion tax strongly suggesting that
minimal field theoretic cosmic strings are a mathematical anomaly rather than a physical
reality right we can then look back at the bottom of telescope data from nanograph
when astrophysicists deeply analyzed the specific spectral shape of the gravitational wave hum they
detected they found that it didn't cleanly match the theoretical signature of a cosmic string at
work anyway the data actually strongly prefers a completely different astrophysical source
the hum perfectly aligns with the stochastic background generated by millions of super massive
black hole binaries right monstrous black holes at the centers of colliding galaxies slowly spiraling
into each other over billions of years churning the fabric of space-time so the extreme theoretical
constraints from asymptotic safety and the empirical telescope observations from nanograph
arrive at the exact same conclusion from completely opposite directions
simple cosmic strings do not exist in our universe the underlying architecture of reality simply does
not support them it is incredibly satisfying when theoretical physics and observational astronomy
shake hands like that even if it means killing a beloved theory yes rare but beautiful we have
witnessed the asymptotic safety framework methodically dismantle horn desky dark
energy by 57 orders of magnitude and crush cosmic strings under an insurmountable complexity tax
this brings us to the philosophical core of the paper right the big picture what does this massive
mathematical teardown mean for the future of how we do physics the paper heavily contrasts the
asymptotic safety framework with the particles that make up the physical physical structure of an
asymptotic safety framework methodically dismantle horn desky dark energy by fifty seven orders of
magnitude and crush cosmic strings under an insurmountable complexity tax this brings us to the
episodes of the scientific theory this paper contrasts the rules from the Kathryn and other
with string theory's Swampland program.
Let's delve into the difference between the Swampland
and what this paper calls the small landscape.
Well, for the better part of three decades,
string theory has dominated the conversation
surrounding quantum gravity.
Yes, it has.
However, a major issue of string theory
is its vastness.
When you compactify the extra dimensions
required by the theory,
you generate an incomprehensible number
of possible vacuum states.
Often cited as 10 to the 500 possible
distinct universes, right?
Exactly.
Each with its own specific laws of physics.
This is the string theory landscape.
To regain any predictive power,
string theorists developed the Swampland program.
The Swampland is essentially
a theoretical sorting mechanism.
It's an attempt to figure out
which low energy effective field theories
can successfully be embedded
into string theory
and which ones are fundamentally incompatible
and belong in the Swampland of broken theories.
Precisely.
But the methodology of the Swampland program
relies heavily on general conjectures.
Conjectures, so guesses.
Heuristic guidelines and educated physical guesses, yeah.
They're based on the thermodynamics of black holes
or the behavior of string dualities.
Okay.
They use rules like the weak gravity conjecture
or the decidered.
conjecture to assert that certain dark energy models or field ranges are likely impossible
yeah it is a powerful conceptual tool but it lacks strict step-by-step computational rigor
in many areas it's like looking at a massive uncharted continent on a map drawing a vague
generalized circle around a swanky looking area and telling architects we strongly conjecture that
if you build a house there it will sink that's a perfect analogy it's a useful guideline but it's
not an engineering proof the small landscape of asymptotic safety however operates on an entirely
different level of precision the small landscape does not rely on conjectures it utilizes rigorous
explicit calculable mathematical mechanisms specifically the functional renormalization
group and the wetterich equation
it
doesn't just guess that the horn desky braiding coupling is incompatible with quantum gravity no
it explicitly traces the beta functions identifies the exact z2 kinetic symmetry
and calculates the coupling to be identically exactly zero it actively computes the 57 order
of magnitude discrepancy yes and it derives the exact number of 42 fermions required for stability
the small landscape isn't a vague map it is a strict computational
structure
which demands a total paradigm shift in cosmological model building a shift explicitly called for in
section 17 of the paper it's a call to action because for a very long time theoretical physics
has relied heavily on bottom-up model building we observe an anomaly in our telescopes like the
accelerated expansion of the universe or the hubble tension and we invent a new mathematical patch to
fix it
different but we
but this paper definitively proves that bottom-up construction is ultimately futile if it ignores the high energy reality the phenomenological patches almost never survive the extreme infinite energy of the big Bang.
the author insists that the community must
transition to top-down model building
We must begin our theoretical convective practice to call the three forces we're currently parts of a Chinese agency mówi this procedure without notice until tomorrow.
opening-end
werendre
burash
weие
me
angscrum
wereren
er個人
construction at the Planck scale. We must start with mathematical frameworks that possess explicit
UV consistency, like a verified non-Gaussian fixed point, and then rigorously calculate the
RG flow down to the macroscopic scale to see what the universe actually permits to exist.
If I'm understanding the underlying mechanics of this entire discussion,
it means the perceived freedom we thought we had in theoretical physics is largely an illusion.
Yeah, that's the sobering truth.
You can mathematically invent all the beautiful, phenomenologically perfect dark energy models you
want, but if they cannot survive the entropic funnel of the renormalization group flow.
If they cannot fit through that incredibly tiny, heavily guarded mathematical gate
of UV consistency at the Planck scale.
They are simply not real. The universe's structural
fillers are not real. The universe's structural fillers are not real.
That is the uncompromising reality this paper presents.
We must respect the mathematical authority of the Planck scale.
Wow.
The Big Bang is not merely a boundary condition that we can ignore while we play with low energy
equations in the present day. It is the fundamental arbiter of what physics is allowed to exist.
We have covered immense ground today. We started with the cracking foundation of
lambda-CDM and the panic of the Hubble tension.
We explored how the functional renormalization group acts as the universe's ultimate gatekeeper,
utilizing the entropic flow of irrelevant couplings to dictate macroscopic reality.
We watched that framework mathematically eviscerate Horndesky dark energy.
Right and impose an impossible 42 particle complexity tax on cosmic strings. The inescapable conclusion is that the universe's
governed by a highly predictive completely unforgiving top-down architecture absolutely
unforgiving but before we conclude this deep dive i want to leave you with a final highly
provocative thought directly from section nine of the paper oh this part is mind-bending it really
is everything we have discussed today the wetterick equation the fixed points the 57 orders of
magnitude it all relies entirely on one massive underlying assumption about the nature of reality
right it relies on what the author calls a polynomial truncation of the effect
of average action and fundamentally it assumes that standard metric geometry
the concept that the distance between two points is the primary foundational
variable of the universe is the ultimate truth it is a profound caveat the paper explicitly
addresses the possibility that at the deepest most fundamental level of quantum gravity
reality might not be built on
polynomial interactions or standard distances at all what if the fundamental variable of the
universe isn't distance but area area the authors touch upon the concept of area metric gravity a
framework loosely related to ideas in Loop quantum gravity and spin foams where the microscopic
fabric of reality provides entirely new degrees of freedom based on geometric areas rather than
point-to-point distances it's a completely different way to build space-time right if
distance is merely an emergent illusion of our low energy macroscopic world and quantum area is the
actual foundational truth at the Planck scale then that rigid structural filter of the universe might
be enforcing a completely different set of mathematical rules that we haven't even begun
to discover yet it suggests that our current understanding of quantum gravity might just
be a shadow cast by a much
stranger infinitely more complex architecture as you look up at the night sky appreciating
the precise elegant physics that governs the cosmos remember that the mathematical waters
are incredibly deep and we are only just beginning to map the currents the universe is actively
filtering out our best guesses but it might be doing so in a geometric canvas we don't even
fully comprehend yet something for you to ponder thank you for joining us on this deep dive into
the underlying architecture
of reality