Welcome to the Deep Dive. Our mission today is pretty ambitious. We are challenging one of the
most basic bedrock assumptions of, well, of all modern science and philosophy. The idea that we
are simply passive observers, that we're just looking at a fixed external universe. We've got
a dense stack of sources today, all diving into foundational physics, into philosophy. And what
they suggest is that reality might actually be, well, more of a negotiation. We're exploring
this framework known as the participatory universe in the realist mode. And the goal is to give
you a shortcut to understanding why accepting our role as participants fundamentally changes
everything. It changes how we think about knowledge, about measurement, about what reality even
is. Exactly. And the central concept that really forces this shift is something we call
interference. Interference. Yeah. And immediately that sounds like, you know, noise or just a
disturbance. But here it's something far more profound. It's the unavoidable inherent link
between a system's representation of its domain. So it's knowledge of the world. It's knowledge
of the world and its own actions within that domain. When that link is truly unavoidable,
it becomes, and I'm quoting here, impossible to stabilize certain features of the world as
objects of knowledge independently of the act of representing them.
You can't separate the map from the map maker's own movements.
You got it.
Okay. Let's unpack that because it sounds a little bit like we're back to philosophical tricks,
but these ideas come straight out of physics, out of computer science. So how is this different
from just having imperfect knowledge or, you know, accidentally disturbing something when you
measure it? That's the crucial question. Imperfect knowledge means the fact is there. It exists. We
just haven't found it yet. Right. Interference means the fact cannot be stabilized until the act of
measurement is complete. And that act itself helps determine the outcome. We can see this in a couple of
really clear ways. First, there's the logical, not the semantic example.
Ah, give us the self-defeating computer paradox. It's a great one.
It's the perfect illustration of what we call negative interference. So imagine you program a
computer to answer this very specific question. Is the answer to this question that's about to be
displayed in the output channel, no?
Okay. I see where this is going. Yeah. If the computer answers yes, it means the displayed
answer is no, which contradicts the yes it just gave. Right. And if the computer answers no,
then the displayed answer is no, which means the answer should have been yes. Yeah. It's a liar
either way. Exactly. Any answer it gives conflicts semantically with the action of giving the answer.
The computer literally cannot stabilize the truth of its statement independently of the output
channel it's using. It's trapped. Right. It's trapped by self-reference. And we see another
version of that in the everyday world, the causal example. This is less about logic and more about
actions defeating predictions. Yeah. The classic example is the boy trying to guess his Christmas
present. His mother is absolutely determined to surprise him. So she waits until Christmas Eve to
buy the gift. The boy's prediction, his guess, directly causes the mother to act to defeat that
prediction. So the prediction itself interferes with the reality it's trying to describe. The attempt to
know the future becomes self-defeating. It does. And we see echoes of this, you know, classically,
think about stock market predictions or political polls. The prediction itself makes people change their
behavior. But classically, we feel like we can mostly contain that. That's the key difference.
In a classical setting, this kind of self-referential interference is usually controlled. We can sort of
channel it and focus it into the future. Right. It affects what happens next. But we can all still
agree on what happened in the past or what's physically around us right now. But, and this is where it gets
really, really interesting. In quantum mechanics, interference is endemic. Endemic.
It's pervasive. It affects the stabilization of properties, even in the present moment.
And this means our fundamental attempts to find things out. Well, they don't have the logic of
measurement that we're used to. Right. Because we're all instinctive realists. We just assume
that when we measure the spin of a particle, we're just revealing a value that was already there.
Like, you know, reading a label off a jar. Precisely. We assume measurement reveals what
was there already or there anyways. But decades of foundational physics Bell's theorems, the study
of decoherence, they all show that we have to deny that assumption. So unmeasured quantum properties just
don't have definite values. They don't. The act of interaction fundamentally prevents us from stabilizing
the properties of that system independently of our attempt to know them.
So we can't treat the microscopic world as there to be known in the same way the future isn't there
to be known. So if we can't stabilize these systems as objective objects, we had to change our whole
philosophical attitude. We have to. We have to shift from the position of the detached observer to the
participant. The observer assumes they are separate, standing outside the system. The participant
recognizes they are part of the unfolding reality. Which means we have to reframe the interaction
itself. We should see quantum events not as passive measurements, but as, as choices.
Ah. Strategic actions. Exactly. I mean, think about it. A choice produces an action that interferes with
what happens next. It's like planting seeds in the spring to get a crop in the fall. You're intervening to
get a result. You're intervening. If you treat the quantum interaction as a knowledge gathering
game, you run into all this paradoxical interference. But if you treat it as a strategic action, the
interference is just. Well, that's the nature of being embedded in the system. This connects beautifully
to John Wheeler's idea of observer participancy. But you're not making it subjective. You're placing it
inside a concrete objective account of physics. That's right. The ability that classical physics
gave us, this, this luxury of separating observation from participation, of treating the world as a pure
object of epistemic attention. Of just looking. Of just looking. Yes. That's revealed to be the special
case, not the generic one. It's a simplifying condition that emerges only under certain circumstances.
We are constantly acting in the environment we're representing. And because of that, the information
we get back will always contain the ripples produced by its own actions. That's a huge shift in perspective.
Yeah. But now we have to go from epistemology, how we know things, to ontology, to what things are.
If reality is this inseparable process, what does that mean for how we figure out the fundamental
building blocks of the universe? This takes us right to the concept of simplicity.
Simplicity. In physics, simplicity isn't just about, you know, pretty equations. It's a
crucial guide for model building, for figuring out what's fundamental. And you measure it by minimizing
the number of degrees of freedom. The fewest independently moving parts, you need to explain everything you see.
That's it. This is what Einstein meant when he said the goal of theory is to make the irreducible
basic elements as simple and as few as possible without having to surrender the adequate representation
of a single datum of experience. Simplicity guides us to truth.
And when we apply that drive to quantum reality, we immediately slam into its strangest feature.
Entanglement, non-separability. These are states that posit non-identical but perfectly correlated
events. So particle A and particle B are separated by a galaxy. Yet if A is measured spin up, B is
instantaneously spin down every single time.
And you see these deep instantaneous constraints across vast distances. So what is the rational
scientific response to a correlation that extreme?
You apply the common source principle. If you see correlated results, the most rational inference
is to trace them back to a common source or a common ground. It is always simpler to assume a shared
origin than to just invent some spooky, unexplained connection between two distant things.
So because the entangled events are correlated, but are demonstrably not connected by any known
signal in 3D space, the interpretive pressure is to see the parts not as independent things at all.
Exactly. But as being grounded in the whole integrated entangled system, this is quantum holism.
The whole is more fundamental than the parts.
Okay, there's great analogy for this.
Yes, Bohm's fish tank. It visualizes this perfectly. Imagine you're watching two TV screens.
Each screen shows the movement of a fish.
Okay, two different images of fish.
And you observe that when the fish on screen one turns left, the fish on screen two instantly turns
right. They're perfectly instantaneously correlated, but you see no signal, no wire passing between the
screens.
So if you were a 2D being living only on the plane of the screens, you'd have to invent some incredibly
complicated theory. So kind of instantaneous communication between the two images.
You would. But we, with our 3D perspective, we know the true source of the correlation.
The two images are just different lower dimensional projections of a single physical 3D fish swimming
in the tank.
Ah.
The correlation isn't due to signals in the 2D space. It's just redundancy. It comes from the common
source, the single beebable fish.
That's a perfect metaphor for holism. The weird correlation in the 2D measurement space
is explained most simply by a single higher dimensional reality, the integrated system,
which is the truly fundamental thing.
And that's the argument. For those who favor quantum holism, the simplicity requirement leaves
them to say the fundamental ontology shouldn't be tiny independent particles, but maybe the entire
cosmos, or the holistic wave function in some higher dimensional space. It's the simplest explanation
for the coordinated randomness we see.
This all paints a picture of a world that is fundamentally inseparable, participatory. But if that's what's really
going on, how do we explain this? Our everyday experience, the stability, the separability, the objectivity
of everything. Why is my coffee mug always in the same place?
We get back to the process that, in a way, saves classical reality. Decoherence.
Decoherence.
Decoherence is a physical mechanism that actively suppresses quantum interference. You can think of it
as the universe smoothing out its own weirdness. When a quantum system interacts with a complex,
noisy, thermal environment.
The billions of air particles all around my mug.
Exactly. The fragile superpositions, the quantumness, it quickly leaks into that environment
and gets scrambled.
So the environment itself is acting like a chaotic, incredibly fast measuring device that
just destroys the possibility of interference.
That's a great way to put it. And this provides the physical mechanism for the emergence of the
classical world, the world of stable knowers and objective objects. Our everyday perceptual
interactions happen in an environment where interference has been washed out, allowing stability to become
the rule, not the exception.
And this brings us to that strange tension we all feel about time. On one hand, you have
the fixed mathematical structure of time and physics, what philosophers call Parmenidian time.
The block universe, where the past, present, and future are all equally real.
The map.
The map. But then we have our subjective, lived experience, Heraclitian time. The feeling of flow,
of passage, of an open future. This really sounds like confusing the map with the territory.
It is absolutely confusing the map with the territory.
The mathematical block universe is an effective description of all possible events,
but it isn't the experience of those events. Our subjective experience of flow and passage
emerges entirely from our perspective as, well, as temporally embedded momentary participants.
We're inside it. Moving through it.
We're inside it. The feeling of the future being open arises because you, the participant,
cannot stabilize your beliefs or your knowledge about the future until you have stabilized your choices.
And because your choice is an action that interferes with the outcome,
the future remains genuinely open to you, even if the underlying physical laws are deterministic.
So the flow and the passage that we feel, they aren't intrinsic properties of the universe itself.
They are, and I'm quoting again, artifacts of changes in the participant's perspective
relative to the fixed physical background.
It's an emergent feature of being an agent inside the process.
And that is the synthesis. The stability, separability, and objectivity we take for granted in classical physics
are not generic features of the cosmos. They are emergent special conditions achieved through decoherence.
And at the deepest level...
Deepest level, the very structure that supports the distinction between self as subject and world as object just,
it disappears. It reveals an underlying inescapable inseparability.
This is genuinely profound. We've moved from the philosophical problem of self-reference interference
to the ontological problem of fundamental structure, simplicity and holism,
and then finally to the subjective problem of experience, this emergent time and flow.
The ultimate takeaway for you here is that the quantum world isn't unknowable
because it's cloaked in some kind of mysticism.
It's unknowable in the classical sense for the very same reason the future is unknowable in the classical sense
because our actions are an inherent interfering part of the unfolding reality.
We aren't just in the audience. We are actors on the stage.
And if we really accept that view, if we start looking at the quantum world not through the logic of passive measurement
but through the logic of strategy and active choice, it raises an extraordinary final question for you to mull over.
What does that participatory structure imply about the nature of free will,
given that our ability to act strategically is itself an emergent feature of what is, at its base,
a deterministic physical universe?
It suggests genuine uncertainty can arise from an internal perspective,
even while the clockwork of the cosmos just keeps on turning.
Oh, no.
There we go.
Thank you.
Woo-hoo.
And then,
where is your religion?
Buying!
No,
no!
no.